Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is ק"ז kuf zayin
107. We are behind, we are on ק"ו עמוד ב', kuf vav
amud bet, but it's a very short דף daf today, so God-willing
we'll catch up. We pick up on ק"ו עמוד ב' kuf vav
amud bet about ten lines from the top, to דף. daf. אמר
רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן. Amra R' Chiya bar Abba
amra R' Yochanan. Okay, so we're dealing with different issues about somebody
who says an object was stolen or is lost, and an oath
he's the one that stole it, he pays the קרן keren and
חומש chomesh and a fifth. And the other thing that we've introduced
is that
if he says it was an אשם, asham, so he pays the
קרן, keren, חומש, chomesh, and a fifth.
A קרן, keren, a חומש, chomesh, and an אשם, asham, thank you,
a קרן, keren, a fifth, and a קרבן. korban. But we've also
introduced the idea which we've seen all the way from the beginning
of מרובה, Meruba, that if he says it's נגנב, nignav, not נגזל
nigzal or not נאבד ne'evad or whatever, נגנב, nignav, and then he
actually is the one holding onto it, he gets the status of
a גנב gannav and he pays כפל. kefel. So now we're going
to build on that idea and take it to its logical conclusion.
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן: Amra R' Chiya bar
Abba amra R' Yochanan: הטוען טענת גנב בפקדון, hatone tanat gannav b'pikadon,
somebody is watching an object and says that it's נגנב nignav and
now he's lying, משלם תשלומי כפל, meshaylem tashlumei kefel,
he pays double. טבח ומכר, tovach u'machar,
if he actually goes ahead, if there are עדים, eidim, right? If
yeah, there are עדים, eidim, right, he doesn't admit it. Then that's
all we know from the תורה, Torah, right? אם לא ימצא הגנב
im lo yimatzei hagannav whatever, אשר ירשיעון אלהים ישלם שנים לרעהו. asher
yarshion Elohim yeshalem shnayim l'rei'eihu.
But now he takes it one step further and says, ah, since
he's going to be paying כפל kefel if he's lying, then he's
a גנב. gannav. Okay, if he's a גנב, gannav, טבח ומכר, tovach
u'machar, if he then slaughtered the animal or sold it, משלם תשלומי
ארבעה וחמשה, meshaylem tashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah,
he'll pay four and five. Let's just go the whole way, make
him a full גנב. gannav. All right. The גמרא Gemara says, הואיל
וגנב משלם תשלומי כפל וטוען טענת גנב משלם תשלומי כפל. ho'il v'gannav
meshaylem tashlumei kefel v'to'ein ta'anat gannav meshaylem tashlumei kefel. Since the גנב
gannav pays כפל kefel and one who claims it was נגנב nignav
pays כפל, kefel, מה גנב שמשלם כפל טבח ומכר משלם תשלומי
ארבעה וחמשה, ma gannav shemushlam kefel tovach u'machar meshaylem tashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah,
just like a גנב gannav who goes ahead and then slaughters or
sells, pays four and five, אף טוען טענת גנב כיון שמשלם תשלומי
כפל טבח ומכר משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמשה, af to'ein ta'anat gannav keivan
shemushlam tashlumei kefel tovach u'machar meshaylem tashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah,
the same way with somebody claims it was נגנב, nignav, he will
also pay four and five if he slaughters and sells it. Okay,
so obviously this is like taking it to its logical conclusion, you
know. But
one could of course question the whole point, like why is a
גנב gannav paying and not a גזלן? gazlan? And the גמרא Gemara
says because a גנב gannav sort of like, you know, I mean
we've raised two reasons: one not in the גמרא, Gemara, that a
גנב gannav who like breaks into somebody's house is more of a
sense of like violation, you know, that occurs like a little bit
closer to home as opposed to cases of like, you know, גזילה.
gezeila. And the גמרא's Gemara reason that this person has like, you
know, it's a theological issue: he's afraid of people, not afraid of
human beings. Neither of those are true by a guy who's טוען
טענת גנב. to'ein ta'anat gannav. I'm sorry, afraid of people not afraid
of God, okay?
So neither of those are true by the guy who's טוען טענת
גנב. to'ein ta'anat gannav. He didn't break into your house and he
doesn't show any like difference, any hypocrisy.
Okay, but for whatever reason the תורה Torah says כפל, kefel, fine.
Okay, so I mean the way חז"ל Chazal read the פסוקים pesukim
it says כפל. kefel. But you know, it still is a bit
of a stretch to say just because it's כפל kefel we're going
to assume the full status of a גנב gannav and all of
these, you know, and therefore the next set of logical conclusions. But
that is the claim here, that if he טבח ומכר tovach u'machar
he pays four and five. Yes.
So you're saying something's just, I must be missing something very basic.
Like he pays four or five, like what if it wasn't an
animal that was the פקדון? pikadon?
No, then it's only כפל, kefel, means in exactly the
same right, exactly the same
circumstances: שור או שה, shor o seh, if it's a שור shor
five, if it's a שה seh four, whole thing.
Okay, I just want small clarity on the theological, like I've like
an act of גזילה, gezeila, couldn't you say that a גזלן gazlan
is afraid of neither? Like it's broad daylight.
Yeah, exactly, he's afraid of neither. At least he's not hypocritical. At
least he at least he doesn't show that he cares about, right,
or at least he shows that he doesn't value human opinion over
divine.
So we have more respect for a גזלן gazlan than for a
גנב? gannav? Exactly. If you're going to do it, do it right.
Exactly. Okay. Okay, so where are we? כיון שמשלם תשלומי כפל וכו'
keivan shemeshaylem tashlumei kefel etc.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
like
this: טוען טענת גנב וכו' to'ein ta'anat gannav etc. The גמרא Gemara
challenges it.
לא, מה לגנב שכן משלם תשלומי כפל שלא בשבועה. lo, ma l'gannav
sheken meshaylem tashlumei kefel shelo b'shvua. A גנב, gannav, the act of
גניבה gneivah automatically he pays כפל. kefel. תאמר בטוען טענת גנב שאינו
משלם תשלומי כפל אלא בשבועה. tomar b'to'ein ta'anat gannav she'eino meshaylem tashlumei
kefel ela b'shvua. But a טוען טענת גנב to'ein ta'anat gannav like
we've been seeing before, you know, there's a whole question as soon
as he makes a claim of denying, you
say
נגזל, nigzal, נאבד ne'evad etc., do
you automatically become a גזלן gazlan are you חייב באונסין chayav b'onsin
and that was not clearly concluded one way or another. But it
was with un-, you know, was definite that by the time you
make a שבועה shvua you have your status, whatever the status is,
גזלן gazlan or גנב, gannav, you're חייב באונסין chayav b'onsin and so
on. takes for granted that the punishment of כפל Kefel only comes
at the time of a שבועה. Shvuah. So it says, so look,
since a שבועה Shvuah is part of what's going on here, implicit
you can say a שבועה Shvuah is just necessary to make you
a גנב. Ganav. But once you're a גנב, Ganav, then four and
five. But you could say it another way. Maybe the reason you're
paying כפל Kefel has something to do with the שבועה, Shvuah, you
know, with the שבועת שקר Shvuat Sheker etc. So you can't how
can you prove anything? This is only because of a שבועה. Shvuah.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמרי לא היקשא היא, Amri lo hekesha
hi, בינאן משיבינן על היקשא. beinan meshivinan al hekesha. No, it's
the categories are linked and you don't challenge something that's explicitly linked.
Now how is it linked? What the גמרא Gemara just did here
wasn't a היקש Hekesh was a מה מצינו Mah Matzinu like an
analogy. This is כפל, Kefel, this is כפל. Kefel. This is four
and five, this should be four and five. But the היקש Hekesh
is you might remember and the גמרא Gemara is about to say
this, that the גמרא Gemara earlier going way back to the פרק
Perek of מרובה, Meruba, learned out from the פסוקים Psukim of אם
ימצא הגנב ישלם שנים im yimatzei hagonav yeshalem shnayim אם לא ימצא
הגנב ונקרב בעל הבית אל האלהים im lo yimatzei hagonav venikrav ba'al
habayit el ha'elohim על אשר ירשיעון אלהים ישלם שנים לרעהו. al asher
yarshun elohim yeshalem shnayim lere'eihu. And according to one read those פסוקים
Psukim it's talking about two scenarios. Okay, one is a real גניבה
Gneivah is משלם
שנים, Meshaleim Shnayim, the other is you're lying and you're taking a
false שבועה Shvuah and therefore you're going to pay. That was one
opinion. That was one opinion. So according to that opinion, they're both
literally in the same פרשה Parsha and that's the היקש. Hekesh. It's
not the analogy that's the היקש, Hekesh, it's that they're both in
the same פרשה. Parsha. And therefore, it doesn't matter if they're not
exactly analogous. Okay the גמרא Gemara says one minute, as Michael says,
הני למאן דאמר חד גנב וחד טוען טענת גנב Hani liman d'amar
chad ganav vechad toen ta'anat ganav שפיר, shafir, that's if the פרשה
Parsha is talking about both scenarios. About the case of a גנב
Ganav and the guy who
claimed it was נגנב. Nignav. אלא למאן דאמר האי אם ימצא הגנב
ואם לא ימצא Ela liman d'amar hai im yimatzei hagonav ve'im lo
yimatzei תרוייהו בטוען טענת גנב, travaihu betoen ta'anat ganav, but according to
the one that says both scenarios in that פרשה Parsha are about
cases of somebody who claimed it was נגנב. Nignav. And the idea
that גנב Ganav pays is from a different פסוק Pasuk חיים שנים
ישלם? Chayim Shnayim Yeshalem? So that the actual place where it says
a גנב Ganav pays two and a גנב Ganav pays four and
five is in a completely different section in the תורה Torah than
where it says a טוען טענת גנב Toen Ta'anat Ganav pays two.
So Michael למימרא, le'meimra, how can you learn one from the other?
Because it's you know, they're not exactly analogous. One has a שבועה
Shvuah and one doesn't. So אמרי Amri you could say גנב הגנב.
Ganav hagonav. It says אם לא ימצא הגנב, im lo yimatzei hagonav,
the extra ה heh is coming to tell you, normally ה heh
might be seen as like an excluding word. Only this classic case.
But here what it's saying is you, the guy who's claiming it
was stolen, you are הגנב, hagonav, you are fully a גנב. Ganav.
Okay so now we're learning it less from
analogy
and more from what we seen as explicit association in the תורה.
Torah. Either they're in the same פרשה Parsha or the תורה Torah
is labeling this guy הגנב hagonav which means he has a full
status of a גנב. Ganav. Okay הגנב הגנב. hagonav hagonav. איבעי, Eivei,
that's the claim. Now okay fine, so we worked through the פסוקים
Psukim or through the logic of the argument. Let's see if the
evidence bears this out, whether other sources are consistent or inconsistent with
this approach.
Rabbi Lindsay, there's one you're calling an analogy, what would you call
the other one? Like a
מה מצינו. Mah Matzinu.
א מה מצינו A Mah Matzinu is an analogy. What
היקש Hekesh is where they're in the same פרשה. Parsha. I would
say the הגנב hagonav is like a ריבוי, ribui, you know, it's
whatever like it's a דרש derash from an extra letter so. Okay.
Does היקש Hekesh require the same con- a shared context?
A היקש Hekesh requires that they are literally linked in the תורה.
Torah. You know, it's not like the cases are analogous.
Somehow they're explicitly some form of linkage.
Exactly. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says איבעי ליה רבי חייא בר
אבא לרבי יוחנן. Eivei lei Rabbi Chiya bar Abba leRabbi Yochanan. Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba challenged Rabbi Yochanan's claims here because oh wait there's
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר, amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar,
oh this is interesting I just noticed this. So Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba who told over this teaching in the name of Rabbi Yochanan,
he was the conduit of Rabbi Yochanan's teaching but he wasn't necessarily
happy with it. So he challenged Rabbi Yochanan's teaching. Okay so he
said the following. Here's the ברייתא. Braitah. היכן שורי. Heichan shori. Guy
says or is this a I forget if it's a ברייתא Braitah
or משנה. Mishna. Might be משנה. Mishna. Anyway he says okay the
guy says where's my ox. You know it's היכן פקדוני, Heichan pikdoni,
there's a משנה Mishna coming up that's similar but I think this
is the ברייתא. Braitah. Okay anyway היכן שורי. Heichan shori. You say
hey Michael where's my ox? נגנב. Nignav. Michael says it was it
was נגנב. Nignav. משביעך
אני Mashbi'acha ani take a שבועה Shvuah ואמר אמן. V'amar amen. He
says yes so he's lying of course. So he is now טוען
טענת גנב. Toen Ta'anat Ganav. He's the one who's a Michael
I know and sure's worth more than an iPhone anyway. Okay he's
lying, he's טוען טענת גנב, Toen Ta'anat Ganav, he takes a שבועה,
Shvuah, we now know he's going to pay כפל. Kefel. Okay ואמי
עידי אמיתו שאכלו. Ve'aimi eidi imito she'achalo. Now witnesses are testifying that
it wasn't נגנב, Nignav, we saw Michael having a lot of nice
steak dinners the other night and we go out and we saw
him eating that ox of yours that he was supposed to be
watching.
No but then it should be four and five.
Oh that's what we're about to ask. So since we know that
he's the one that actually took it and it wasn't נגנב, Nignav,
משלם תשלומי כפל. meshaleim tashlumei kefel. He pays כפל. Kefel. So this
is going to be a big challenge to Rabbi Yochanan. Because והא
הכא v'ha hacha he's after the כזית בשר k'zayit basar and he
hasn't שחט. shachat. Michael couldn't- He's been eating the steaks out of
my שור shor unless he שחט shechted it. Because he's so right,
so therefore he should be paying four and
five וקתני v'katani תשלומי כפל. tashlumei kefel. That's the only תשלומי כפל.
tashlumei kefel. תשלומי כפל tashlumei kefel אין, in, only כפל, kefel, תשלומי
ארבעה וחמישה tashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah no, four and five no. How do
you get it? Now I wonder why the גמרא Gemara didn't just
answer like well, you know, what if they didn't see the act
of שחיטה? shechitah? You can infer שחיטה shechitah like they basically, you
know, saw the ox, then saw a dead ox with blood running
out of its neck and then saw Michael having a barbecue, but
they never actually saw him שחט, shecht, right? So, you know, how
much, you know, normally do you need guys like, normally to like
to give a like מלקות malkut or מיתה mitah you need direct
testimony, it's not enough circumstantial. ממון mamon sometimes it can be circumstantial.
This is a קנס. knas. And pretty much we tend to assume
that קנס knas is sort of similar to the corporal punishment that
you would need direct testimony. So I don't know why the גמרא
Gemara couldn't just say that it was like, you know, that it
was what do you call it, that Michael that we didn't directly
see the act of שחיטה? shechitah? But it's not going to say
that. So since Michael clearly must have שחט shechted it, if רבי
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is right he should be paying four and five.
So the
גמרא Gemara says כגון שאכלו נבילה. k'gon she'achalo neveilah. Alright. So, you
know, Michael is not just one of those people who is super
פרום frum and he only eats גלאט כשר glatt kosher but then
he steals and he cheats. No, he's consistently not פרום. frum. So
he's going to go ahead and steal my שור, shor, he's not
going to שחט shecht it. So he ate it נבילה. neveilah. He
shot it in the head, he didn't שחט shecht it, and therefore
he's not going to pay me four and five. The גמרא Gemara
says ולישני ליה v'lishnei leh why not answer כגון שאכלו טריפה? k'gon
she'achalo treifah? Alright, let's you know, how about I mean you know,
maybe there's something that's more seen as like I don't know repulsive
about a Jew eating a נבילה neveilah than eating a טריפה. treifah.
Why do you have to run to the case of נבילה, neveilah,
why not say he שחט shechted it but it was a טריפה?
treifah? Okay, so he's still עבר over on a לאו lav by
eating this, but that's another scenario where he wouldn't be חייב chayav
four and five. Now is that true? If you do an act
of שחיטה shechitah but you don't make the meat כשר kosher because
it's a טריפה treifah but you did an act of שחיטה, shechitah,
are you חייב chayav for four and five? That's the debate of
שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shechitah she'einah re'uyah. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
we didn't want to give that answer. כרבי מאיר דאמר שחיטה שאינה
ראויה שמה שחיטה. k'Rebbi Meir d'amar shechitah she'einah re'uyah shemah shechitah.
No, no, no. Because we want this we're going we פסק pasken
like רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir or you want this to work even
according to רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir who says that if there's even
if you did an act of שחיטה shechitah even if the meat
did not become מותר, muttar, even if for example the animal was
a טריפה, treifah, since you did the act of שחיטה shechitah you're
still going to be חייב chayav a four and five. It still
constitutes an act of שחיטה. shechitah. Okay, so we couldn't say that
he שחט shechted it and it was טריפה, treifah, the only scenario
that he ate it and that he's not going to be חייב
chayav is that he ate it נבילה. neveilah. The גמרא Gemara says
ולישני ליה בבן פקועה. v'lishnei leh b'ben paku'ah. Ah, how about I'll
give you another scenario where he doesn't have to שחט shecht and
he can be eating it. This animal was born, the שור shor
that Michael stole, Michael knew what he was doing when he chose
to steal this שור shor because this שור shor actually had a
very unusual birth. It's sort of like you know Shakespeare by not
of woman born. Right. Okay, so in this case the mother was
שחט shechted when the mother was pregnant and the שור shor then
was born after the mother had died, after the mother was שחט.
shechted. Because the שור shor at that time it was a calf
was in its mother's womb when the mother was שחט, shechted, it
is considered to be pre-שחט. shechted.
And therefore even if it is walking around and you know and
now it's this huge שור, shor, you don't need you can go
ahead and rip off a limb and eat it and you can
just shoot it in the head and eat it because it's already
pre-שחט. shechted. It's like a walking piece of meat
that הלכתית halachically it's considered to already be שחט. shechted.
And therefore Michael didn't have to שחט shecht it in order to
eat it. What?
That wouldn't be אבר מן החי. ever min hachai. That's right.
Yeah, exactly. So by I have to tell you, well let's see
the answer and then I'll say something about it. So it says
maybe that was the case. So the גמרא Gemara says no כרבי
מאיר k'Rebbi Meir again and therefore everyone can agree and therefore everybody
that could be a case where he could be eating it without
having שחט shechted and even eating כשר kosher meat. He wouldn't have
to say he ate
נבילה. neveilah. The גמרא Gemara says no כרבי מאיר דאמר בן פקועה
טעון שחיטה k'Rebbi Meir d'amar ben paku'ah ta'un shechitah that even a
בן פקועה ben paku'ah you have to שחט shecht maybe דרבנן drabbanan
because of like a מראית עין marit ayin case or whatever the
case is we didn't we want it to fit even within that
context so we could not say that so we had to say
you want it to work according to all positions we had to
say he ate it נבילה. neveilah. Now I have to tell you
whenever any ישיבה yeshiva guy ever learned about בן פקועה, ben paku'ah,
the first thing that they you say is like, 'Hey, I've got
this great idea, why don't we start this בן פקועה ben paku'ah
farm of בן פקועה ben paku'ah animals intentionally do it and then
breed animals because even the children of the children of the children
of a בן פקועה ben paku'ah don't need שחיטה.' shechitah. So once
you get a like you start with enough בן פקועה ben paku'ah
animals that you make sure you know you get then you get
you know some bulls and some cows etc. and from that point
on you never have to do any כשר שחיטה. kosher shechitah.
No and also שחט shecht you know you can cook it in
milk of the cow that was שחט shechted it's פליישיג fleishig milk.
No?
Yeah, but let's not go there.
Anyway, the other point though is that you might not have to
worry about a lot of other things, like about גיד הנשה Gid
Hanasheh and all these other things because you just see it as
a piece of meat of the mother, not as sort of its
own animal. So that maybe it, you know, you get away with
the whole thing. Anyway, so we would learn this in ישיבה yeshiva
and all have a good laugh about this possibility.
Anyway, I think that right now, actually in the last year or
two, somebody is really working on doing this for real. They're actually
trying.
I just found it, benpakuameat.com. There you go. However, the Rabbi who
certified them quit, so they're trying to find a new one.
Are they actually offering like salami and the whole thing?
At the moment they're not offering anything.
Okay, so this
is the difference between a men's שיעור shiur and a women's שיעור.
shiur. This is not a question that comes up. We look at
it and we go oh, the poor
mother. Right, exactly.
This is the pastoral counseling side. All right. Well, yeah, okay. So,
okay, we're
going to start a Kickstarter campaign. Invest now, you'll get the free...
okay, any money as your graduate students... All right. All right, enough,
moving on. Enough, moving on.
Okay, so וליחזי ליה דעמד בדין. V'lichzei lei de'amad b'din. Ah, I
got another case where Michael could have eaten it and be פטור
patur and and still not pay four and five. Now we already
had the court case, that I already sent, you know, told Dov
you have my animal and he said I didn't and lied, and
it was נגנב, nignav, took a שבועה, shvuah, and then before he
ate it, we actually, this is a very bizarre read of the
ברייתא braita because it's like it's much more it's a much more
complicated read of the ברייתא. braita. Before he ate it, we proved
that he had stolen it and we had a whole court case
and then afterwards it came and said he ate it. So what
would the court case have done in the middle? It would have
interrupted his status as a גנב. ganav. Once it's been proved that
he stole it, then he no longer is a גנב. ganav. Then,
like, it's known, you know, what he's done and if he keeps
it to himself he's a גזלן. gazlan. Okay, so it says like
this, וליחזי ליה דכא... V'lichzei lei deka... where am I, דעמד
בדין ואמרו לו צא תן לו. de'amad b'din ve'amru lo tze ten
lo. And the בית דין Beis Din told him, Michael, go pay
Dov. דאמר רבה De'amar Rabbah צא תן לו tze ten lo after
the בית דין Beis Din said to a גנב, ganav, whether it's
the טוען טענת גנב, to'en ta'anat ganav, whether it's a normal גנב,
ganav, they found a גנב, ganav, he was schlepped to court, they
found him guilty, they said go pay the guy. And if afterwards
rather than paying the guy he went home and שחט shachted it,
טבח ומכר פטור. tavach umachar patur. Right? After you've been found guilty
in court, there's no continuation of your act of גניבה. gneiva. Right?
It's now known that it's the other guy's thing and if you
decide to שחט shacht it now you're doing a new act of
גזילה gzeila on the guy's object and you're no longer a גנב.
ganav. It's not a continuation of that act. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama,
what's the reason? כיון דפסקו למילתא, Keivan d'pasku lemilta, it was already
ruled that way. וטבח ומכר הוה גזלן. V'tavach umachar hava gazlan. וגזלן
לא משלם ארבעה וחמישה. Vegazlan lo meshalem arba'ah vechamishah. Everybody knows now
you're stealing Dov's object. If they judge חייב
אתה ליתן לו, chayav ata liten lo, they didn't yet say go
pay. They didn't like give the sheriff the order to collect. They
said you're liable but they haven't exactly mandated yet that you hand
it over. In that case, interestingly, וטבח ומכר חייב. v'tavach umachar chayav.
The גנב ganav would still be חייב. chayav. His status of a
גנב ganav is still continuous from the previous status.
Means he didn't officially record the ruling.
Yeah, it seems to be between חייב אתה ליתן לו chayav ata
liten lo and צא תן לו.
tze ten lo.
His status I know but it's
but they have not given actually like, you know, a court can
find somebody guilty and then you actually need that it be handed
over like we would say you need it to be handed over
to the sheriff now and the sheriff has I start to forget
what it's called in secular law but he actually now is has
a like license to go and to seize the property. It's phase
number two. What was the sentence? He was sentenced. No, חייב. chayav.
No, he was just was not told now we are issuing a
mandate so you must hand it over within the next two weeks
or something like that. No, you Michael are found to be a
גנב ganav and you owe Dov, you know, two thousand dollars. Oh,
so if you owe. The next thing is we write out a
writ and say you have one week to pay Dov, go pay
him as soon as possible. That is seen conceptually as a separate
stage. Okay and the difference is is that in both cases we
know what he's done, okay, but is he still within his identity
as a גנב ganav and his relationship to this object is the
object he stole, all right, and he's just so or has this
sort of whole identity and relationship shifted. So from the moment we
say just because you're חייב, chayav, you know, somehow that's not enough
to change your status but when we say you have to pay,
give him the cow back, okay, then it's no then that cow
is now seen as something that's a like I, you know, my
like it's reestablished my relationship with it, okay, and he's no longer
continued to still sort of be defined as a גנב ganav vis-a-vis
that if he were to take. that cow is now seen as
something that's reestablished my relationship with it, and he's no longer continued
to still sort of be defined as a גנב ganav vis-a-vis that.
If he would take that cow, that would be a new seizing
of property from me. Okay, so once they said you have to
give me back the property and reestablished my rights to that property,
if he were to take it, that would be a new act
of taking. It wouldn't be a continuation of the old status. Something
that was confusing to me before is we used to differentiate, as
far as I remember, maybe I'm wrong, between נגמר דין Nigmar Din
and not. Right. So what is this? There are two statuses? That's
correct. And this comes up a lot in סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. I mean,
I can't right now give you the laundry list of the differences,
but there's definitely like to what, at what stage does the קנס
knas convert to ממון mamon is an interesting question, right? You're חייב
chayav to me כפל, kefel, right? So that כפל kefel thing is
like the extra part is a קנס. knas. After בית דין Beit
Din rules that you have to pay, at what stage does it
become ממון mamon and not קנס? knas? After they say חייב אתה
chayav ata or they say צא תן לו? tzei ten lo? So
this difference between חייב אתה chayav ata and צא תן לו, tzei
ten lo, I know it sounds trivial almost, but the גמרא Gemara
actually in a number of places has it as a difference in
terms of what's considered נגמר דין. Nigmar Din. Well, there're two stages
of נגמר דין. Nigmar Din.
These are both נגמר דין?
Nigmar
Din? Yeah, exactly.
I just don't see conceptually why it's not what we call sentencing.
First the guy is...
It is sentencing. It's sentencing.
Right, the guy's been declared guilty, come back two weeks from now
and we're going to give you the mandate of what you have
to do, that's called sentencing.
Right. So he's sentenced, but somehow the fact that it is he's
not...
He's been declared guilty.
He's been declared guilty and he hasn't been sentenced yet.
Right, that's right.
Right. Okay, but the sentencing is also we don't know how many
years in prison we're going to give you. Right. Here we know
how much we're going to give you. We just have not yet,
you know, if you know... We just have not yet like sort
of issued the order. We issued the order for you to now
be like taken and put into, you know, taken away by the
state or something, you know. It's like we haven't issued the order
to act on it. That's the only difference.
And the sentence is the number of years.
I know, but that's still חייב אתה. chayav ata. That's still at
the חייב אתה chayav ata stage. The mandate? Sentencing is still similar
to
חייב אתה. chayav ata. What is your obligation? Okay, צא תן לו
tzei ten lo is the order to act on it. Alright, I
get it. I get why it's hard to understand why it matters.
Alright, moving on. Okay, anyway, חייב
אתה וצא תן לו ודוכתא קמיעסקינן. chayav ata u'tzei ten lo v'duchta
kamias'kinan. מאי טעמא? כל כמה דלא פסקיה להלכתא, mai ta'ama? kol kama
d'lo paskei l'hilchata, as long as it hasn't been like cut, you
know, cut clear, you know, seal, or maybe a seal, or you
know, severed maybe could also be a way of saying it. Like
you know, your previous status has been severed now because the גנב
ganav status, because now we've reestablished the owner's rights, you know, relationship
to his object, ואכתי גנב הוא, v'achati ganav hu, so you're still
in your previous status, you're a גנב ganav who's been found guilty,
but you're still a גנב, ganav, and to continue to do it
is to continue to act in your גנב ganav role. Okay, so
anyway, I get why it's hard to see exactly why it makes
a difference. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara continues, אמרי, amri, okay, so anyway,
so what's the... wait, wait, wait, what's the question? The גמרא Gemara
says like this, וליסני ליה כגון גנב ועמד בדין ואמרו לו צא
תן לו. v'lisni lei k'gon ganav v'amad b'din v'amru lo tzei ten
lo.
So why not, why not just give that answer that we said
צא תן לו tzei ten lo to Michael and then he slaughtered
it and that's why he's not paying four and five? וליסני ליה?
v'lisni lei? Right, so the גמרא Gemara says, ולטעמיך, u'l'ta'ameich, so like
any good Jew, rather you know, answers a question with a question.
So you want me to say why don't we give an example
that the court had issued צא תן לו? tzei ten lo? I've
got another answer that that we could have given to deal with
this issue why Michael isn't paying four and five. וליסני ליה בשותף
שטבח. v'lisni lei b'shutaf she'tavach.
Maybe he was a partner? Two people stole it and if only
one of them does the slaughtering without the other person's knowledge, then
no... then there's no four and five. Because it says four and
five and not four halves and five halves. Okay, so since he
acted without the other person's knowledge, he can't be חייב chayav the
full amount, and since he can't be חייב chayav the full amount,
he can't be חייב chayav even part. So here's another answer we
could have said, Michael was a שותף. shutaf.
But it's still be חייב כפל? chayav kefel?
Yes, but we're trying to explain how could it be that you
were טוען טענת גנב toen ta'anat ganav and then you slaughtered it
and ate it without being paying four and five. So one answer
was you slaughtered it after... why don't we... one was you just
ate it as an נבילה. neveilah. The other answer was you slaughtered
it after צא תן לו. tzei ten lo. Okay, and we said
why didn't we say that? So we said well, we could say
another thing. Why don't we say that you slaughtered it שלא
לדעת חבירו? shelo l'daat chaveiro? So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמרי חדא מתרתי נקט. amri chada m'tartei nakat. Fine, I could have
given that answer. We have one out of two or three reasons.
I could have said צא תן לו, tzei ten lo, I chose
to say this. Of course the answer you understand why the גמרא
Gemara wants an answer other than נבילה. neveilah. Like somehow it wants
Michael maybe to be a גנב ganav but not also to eat
טרף. treif. Okay, so the other answers don't have him eating טרף
treif and the גמרא Gemara says that's fine, we could have said
that. I don't think I'm at the קוף kof yet, but whatever.
It's okay, let's see how it comes out. Thank you.
Anyway, so the... okay, now I don't know, I haven't looked in
the ראשונים, Rishonim, but I did not see in רש"י Rashi תוספות,
Tosafot, I don't understand how it could be talking about a case
of a שותף. shutaf. Michael here was a טוען טענת גנב. toen
ta'anat ganav. What's the case that he was a שותף shutaf in
the גניבה? geneivah? I gave it to him and Charlie to watch
combined and they both took a שבועת שוא shvuat shav to me?
So that's the case? Maybe. I mean, they both took a שבועת
שקר shvuat sheker to me? So that's the case?
Maybe. I mean...
That could be, but that's not what רש"י Rashi says. You're saying
that רש"י Rashi says שותפין שגנבו. shuttaphin shegannavu. רש"י Rashi
says it would have to be that you gave it to two
people to watch and then they both swore falsely to me to
something like that.
That's my question. Do you have to, do you have to give
it to two people? Can you give, can you give it to
me as a פיקדון pikadon and then you go on vacation? And
then I call Michael, and listen, I gotta go out for a
day, come over, you be the שומר shomer with me, like, take
my place.
Well that's שומר שמסר לשומר, shomer shemasar leshomer, that's a whole other
separate. It would have to been מראש merosh I gave it to
two, but again, you know, it's like the question of שבועת העדות,
shevuat haeidut, like how are you מחייב mechayev somebody that requires two
people to do it in concert, like, I didn't know he was
gonna swear, I didn't know what, anyway. All right, moving on though.
Okay, this is the claim though that you become a full גנב
gannav and you pay כפל. kefel. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like, אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Chiyya
bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan. א טוען טענת גנב באבידה. A toen
ta'anat gannav baaveidah. Right? And I think we passed this way, to
the degree whatever you talked about פוסקין. poskin. אמר רבי חייא בר
אבא אמר רבי יוחנן.
Amar Rabbi Chiyya bar
Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan. א טוען טענת גנב באבידה. A toen ta'anat
gannav baaveidah. So we
good, we're just spitting out different הלכות halachot about טוען טענת גנב,
toen ta'anat gannav, you know about somebody who swears falsely about a
פיקדון. pikadon. So somebody says it's a גנב gannav by a case
of an אבידה. aveidah. The normal case is we can make me
the bad guy now, Michael gave me his object to watch, and
then he says where is it and I say נגנב nignav and
I swear on high פיקדון. pikadon. But let's say that wasn't the
case. Let's say I was walking down the street and I saw
on the street, oh my god, look at this gorgeous new Samsung
phone, I've always wanted one, and on the back it sort of
has a sticker that says Michael Axon, so I just tear that
off, right, I'm gonna keep it to myself. And then Michael says
what happened to that, I heard you found my Samsung phone, I
say yeah I did but you know, נבך נגנב. nebach nignav. I
was gonna return it to you but it got stolen. So I'm
a טוען טענת גנב באבידה. toen ta'anat gannav baaveidah. So it's the
same thing, I was watching his object and then a שומר אבידה
shomer aveidah is חייב chayav to watch an object, okay, and then
I decided to keep it to myself. The difference being that he
never entrusted it to me. So there's no, you know, that sense
of betrayal and that relationship isn't there, it means still the, you
know, the stealing is there. So what's the הלכה? halacha? Do I
pay כפל? kefel? Okay, א טוען טענת גנב באבידה משלם תשלומי כפל.
A toen ta'anat gannav baaveidah meshalem tashlumei kefel. מאי טעמא? mai taama?
What's the reasoning? דכתיב dechitiv על כל אבידה אשר יאמר כי הוא
זה עד האלהים יבא דבר שניהם אשר ירשיען אלהים ישלם שנים לרעהו.
al kol aveidah asher yomar ki hu zeh ad haelohim yavo devar
sheneichem asher yarshian Elohim yeshalem shenayim lere'eihu. So the case about taking
an oath and paying double etc. is introduced in the תורה Torah
by the phrase it says, you know, כי יתן איש אל רעהו,
ki yitten ish el re'eihu, you know, what is it, כסף או
כלים לשמור וגונב מבית האיש, kesef o cheilim lishmor vegunnav mibeit haish,
right, so it says and then it says על כל אבידה. al
kol aveidah. So it starts by saying פיקדון pikadon and then it
says any lost object. So he says let's take the תורה Torah
literally, it doesn't have to be a פיקדון, pikadon, even if you're
watching a lost object. איתיביה רב אבא בר ממל לרבי חייא בר
אבא. Eitivei Rav Abba bar Mamal leRabbi Chiyya bar Abba. What? Yeah.
He asked him, כי יהיה ברייתא ki yehei baraita that says not
that way, or seems to say not that way. When a person
gives, כי יתן
איש, ki yitten ish, when a man gives something to somebody to
watch, this is again the פרשה parshah of טוען טענת גנב. toen
ta'anat gannav. אין נתינת קטן כלום. ein netinat katan kelum. It has
to be an איש. ish. If a minor gave something to somebody
to watch, you know, then that's not a legally binding type of
a transaction and the person doesn't assume obligations of שמירה shemirah and
then if he swears falsely he doesn't pay כפל. kefel. He's פטור.
patur. Yeah. I mean, but there's a question if he even has
חיוב שומר, chiyuv shomer, like if it was פשיעה peshiah would he
be חייב chayav at all anyway? ואין לי אלא שנתנו כשהוא קטן,
veein li ella shenetano keshehu katan, I only know this פרשה parshah
doesn't apply if the object was given when the owner was a
minor. ותבעו כשהוא קטן utevau keshehu katan and then was demanded back
when he was a minor and there's no, and that case of
שבועה shevuah wouldn't pay כפל. kefel. נתנו כשהוא קטן ותבעו כשהוא גדול.
netano keshehu katan utevau keshehu gadol. What if he gave it when
he was a minor but then he had his בר מצוה bar
mitzvah and then he demanded it back now that he's an
adult? מניין minayin that even that case you don't pay כפל kefel
on the שבועה? shevuah? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar
עד האלהים יבא דבר שניהם. ad haelohim yavo devar sheneichem. So it
says כי יתן איש ki yitten ish and שניהם, sheneichem, I don't
know, somehow
it's
linked in עד שתהא נתינה ותביעה שוים כאחד. ad shetehei netinah uteviah
shavin keechad. Maybe because of שניהם. sheneichem. שניהם sheneichem but both of,
so both parties have to be adults originally, I guess. The two
we referred to earlier. Right, maybe, fine. So therefore you have to
be in the same, if you needed it to be
in an adult status now, if you weren't in an adult status
when you gave it over, there's not going to be any liability
of the שבועה. shevuah. Okay, so now we got a question though.
ואי סלקא דעתך vei salka deitach if you're right that an אבידה
aveidah is חייב chayav in this שבועה, shevuah, he says I don't
get it. So when this pre-בר מצוה bar mitzvah boy gave me
this object, it wasn't an entrusting that came with any obligations. But
then he becomes an adult. And then what's happening? I'm holding onto
somebody's object that's not mine, right, and just the fact is I'm
holding onto this, you know, to this person's object. So how's that
different than an אבידה? aveidah? An אבידה aveidah there was no act
of entrusting that came with obligations, but the... The very fact that
I'm holding on to the object of somebody obligates me to watch
it and to protect it. And then so if my שבועה shevuah
makes me pay כפל kefel for an אבידה, aveidah, why should this
be any different? It goes parallel, there is no act of entrusting.
So the גמרא Gemara says, you have to try to
find the owner, הכרזה hachrazah and all the other things that
would go for an אבידה. aveidah. Yeah. אמר ליה: Amar lei: No,
הכא במאי עסקינן hacha bemai askinan כגון שאכלו כשהוא קטן. kegon she'achalo
keshehu katan.
So the גמרא Gemara says, so first try to assume you're right,
they are similar cases. And but this case where you don't pay
כפל kefel when he demands it when he's an adult is when
you had already stolen it or consumed it when he was a
minor. But if your act of גניבה gneivah occurred when he was
an adult, maybe you would pay כפל. kefel. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אבל כשהוא גדול מאי? aval keshehu gadol mai? And what are
you, what are you trying to say? You're trying to say that
if the guy stole it or, you know, ate consumed it after
the kid had become an adult, הכא נמי דמשלם, hacha nami demishalem,
then you would pay כפל? kefel? אי הכי, Ei hachi, if that's
true, עד דתני ad detani עד שיהיו נתינה ותביעה שווים כאחד, ad
she'yehu netinah utviah shavim ke'echad, why does the ברייתא braita say you're
not חייב כפל chayav kefel until the giving and the demand is
when he's an adult? You don't need that both to be when
he is an adult. ליתני הכי Litni hachi עד שתהא אכילה ותביעה
שווים כאחד. ad she'tehei achilah utviah shavim ke'echad.
You need the act of גניבה gneivah to be when the guy
is an adult. So clearly if the giving was when he was
a minor, he's off the hook. So how is it different than
finding an אבידה? aveidah? Let's see the answer. אמר ליה: Amar lei:
תני. Tani. So the first answer is a weak answer, and something
let's switch the gears so. עד שתהא אכילה ותביעה שווים כאחד. ad
she'tehei achilah utviah shavim ke'echad. Fine, you're right. As long as you
stole it when he became an adult, you're חייב chayav even if
it gave it to you when he's a minor. Which is obviously
the weak answer. רב אשי אמר: Rav Ashi amar: רב אשי Rav
Ashi says, no no no, let's challenge the comparison. לא דמי, Lo
dami, it's not similar. אבידה Aveidah קאתי מכח בן דעת. ka'ati mikoach
ben daat. ההוא לא אתי מכח בן דעת. Hahu lo ati mikoach
ben daat.
Even though there is no act of entrusting by the אבידה, aveidah,
when I found an אבידה, aveidah, I found the object of an
adult, and that created obligations of שמירה shmirah to that adult. Okay,
so there are obligations of שמירה shmirah that began with my relationship
with this object even though there was no act of entrusting. Whereas,
and that's why when I then go ahead and טוען טענת גנב,
toen taanat ganav, I'm חייב. chayav. But the case of the קטן,
katan, there was, my original relationship with this object did not entail
any obligations. Okay, and therefore because even if later he becomes an
adult and there are obligations, it was not my initial relationship to
this object. So in both cases there wasn't an act of entrusting,
but at least once it did start with actual legal obligations to
the
other person, like that you do have obligations to
a קטן katan when you find an אבידה? aveidah?
So I
wonder, you
know, it's an interesting question.
I mean logically what you're saying is of course true, you know,
but I don't know if you find the אבידה aveidah of a
קטן. katan. Yeah, I assume you have to return it to him
because it's not your object, but you know you don't own it.
But do you have the same חיובה שמירה? chiyuvey shmirah? Right? When
the גמרא Gemara has a whole discussion is it שומר אבידה שומר
חנם או שומר שכר? shomer aveidah shomer chinam o shomer sachar? Right?
And then you're negligent and then would you have to reimburse and
so on? I
yeah, because it could be that the תורה Torah doesn't recognize any
legal, any legal obligations to people who are not בני דעת bnei
daat to
begin with, the קטן, katan, right? He can't own it, he could
have inherited it.
I do have to return it, but let's say I'm negligent and
it gets destroyed, do I have to pay him back? Right? You're,
the distinction is a much narrower one, that you do
have obligations to him, but it's obligations that come about בן דעת.
ben daat.
Right,
I hear your point. I mean, I just don't know the answer,
like I don't know why if I really do have obligations of
שמירה shmirah to the קטן, katan, why the fact that he's not
a, you're saying it's a technical point, right? There's no, there's no
logic, it's just a technical point that the whole הלכה halacha and
the הלכה halacha I learned requires that the initial relationship started with
a בן דעת. ben daat. Maybe you're right, but I, I do
have to actually look into it. It's not as פשוט pashut to
me as it is to you. Like on the one hand, right,
if you're, exactly. On the one hand, like we said before, you
know, if you're חובל קטן, chovel katan, if you're מזיק קטן, mazik
katan, like you are, you do have like, you know, liability to
him. But that's if you create damages. But in terms of something
that's more sort of like transactional, not tort, but you know a
sense of like liability, a חיובה שמירה, chiyuvey shmirah, to me it's
not so clear that you have that to a קטן katan if
you find a קטן's katan אבידה. aveidah. I have to look into
it, it's a good question. Do you want to add something, חברה?
Chavra? All right, we're still, we still haven't finished. Anyway,
no, so we said, you could be right, you could be that
you're חייב כפל chayav kefel by an אבידה aveidah as long as
it's an אבידה aveidah of a בן דעת, ben daat, and the
case of a קטן katan is irrelevant. So this position still stands,
has not, has not been contradicted. Okay, now we turn to another
statement of רבי חייא בר אבא בשם רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Chiyya bar
Abba beshem Rabbi Yochanan, which is going to lead to that huge
תוספות Tosafot we're about to see. Okay, hope, hopefully help us catch
up. דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, De'amar Rabbi Chiyya
bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, הטוען טענת גנב בפקדון, hata'en taanat ganav
bepikadon, back to being saying it's a גניבה gneivah went by a
case of a
פקדון, pikadon, אינו חייב, eino chayav, the חיובא דכפל chiyuva de'kefel is
only. עד שיכפור במקצת ויודה במקצת. ad sheyichpor b'miktzas v'yodeh b'miktzas. So
here we have this crazy idea, okay, and anybody who's learned the
beginning of המפקיד Hamapkid knows it's not crazy. I mean if you
say it long enough, it's not crazy. Which
is that we all know there's a classic שבועה shvua in the
תורה Torah of a מודה במקצת. modeh b'miktzas. Michael, you owe me
$100. No, I only owe you $50. If he would have denied
owning me nothing, he's off. המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi meichaveiro alav
hara'aya. If he would have said, but I sent 50, he concedes
part, so he takes the שבועה shvua on the other part. Okay,
and that's based on the פסוק pasuk אשר יאמר כי הוא זה
עד האלהים יבא דבר שניהם. asher yomar ki hu zeh ad ha'elohim
yavo dvar shneihem. You concede to part of it, yes, this is
the part I owe you, but I don't owe you the other
part, you have to take a שבועה. shvua. The problem is that
that פרשה parsha of אשר יאמר כי הוא זה asher yomar ki
hu zeh is right in the context of our פרשה parsha of
a guy who says that it was נגנב, nignav, right? He's טוען
טענת גנב בפיקדון toein ta'anas ganev b'pikadon and it says he admits
to part of it. So what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan basically says
is, the חיוב chiyuv of שומרים shomrim in general, it's not discussed
explicitly here, this is part of what תוספות Tosfos developed, but you'll
trust me on this. The חיוב chiyuv of שומרים shomrim in general,
whether Michael here's a שומר, shomer, whether his claim is it got
stolen, whether his claim is that it got, an accident happened, the
dog ran out into the street and you know whatever got hit
by a car, some whatever אונס, ones, גניבה, gneiva, whatever he claims,
okay,
he will only take a שבועה. shvua. We assume if I say
to Michael, what happened to my object, and he says it was
נגנב, nignav, that I'm entitled to say take a שבועה. shvua. That's
the שבועת השומרים. shvuas hashomrim. Take a שבועה shvua that that's actually,
how do I know that's what happened? Take a שבועה shvua that
that's actually what happened. Okay, so he says you Michael, I can
only make Michael take a שבועת השומרים shvuas hashomrim if there is
an also שבועת מודה במקצת shvuas modeh b'miktzas going on here. And
basically the scenario is I gave him, if it was an object
like three cows, okay, to make it simple. I gave him $100,
okay, and I said Michael what happened to the $100 I gave
you or whatever? And he said well here, $20 I still have,
take back the
$20. $20 you're lying, you only gave me $80, you didn't give
me $100. And as far as the other $60 is concerned, an
accident happened. So there's like a מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzas taking place
and only because of the מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzas, right, thing that
would exist independent of the שבועת שומרים, shvuas shomrim, can I make
him take a שבועה shvua that it was נגנב. nignav.
So if it was your dog and it was your scenario, got
hit by a car, I don't have to swear?
I don't have to swear, I just say נגנב, nignav, according to
this, right? Which is like completely against what we assume, that every
שומר shomer has to back up his claim about what happened with
a שבועה. shvua. And this is saying any claim that a שומר
shomer makes is only if there's also two other pieces of what's
going on.
Like if the aliens abducted him and I'd still be believed?
I mean all right, I don't know, that's a different point. Okay,
but anyway, any other claim, okay,
any statement of what happened, there has to also be I concede
here is something that I do owe you and I'm giving you
that, and here is something that I'm denying I ever owed you,
and as far as this claim about what happened, okay, that's the
piece I'm going to take a שבועה shvua on. All right, so
only one שבועה shvua in the end is taken? Well, the שבועה
shvua would include all the pieces of it, but you're only going
to make the שבועת השומרים shvuas hashomrim if there's also a מודה
במקצת modeh b'miktzas going on. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן הטוען טענת גנב בפיקדון אינו חייב עד שיכפור במקצת ויודה במקצת.
amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan hatoein ta'anas ganev b'pikadon
eino chayav ad sheyichpor b'miktzas v'yodeh b'miktzas. You have to deny part
of what was given to you, you have to admit to part,
and then you have to claim the other part was stolen. Three
pieces.
So if not, it's always just קרן? keren?
Right, and there's no
שבועה. shvua. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? What's the reason? דאמר קרא כי
הוא זה, d'amar kra ki hu zeh, okay, which in the context
of taking a שבועה shvua about what happened, it says כי הוא
זה, ki hu zeh, there's also a מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzas that
is a necessary framing to then take the שבועה shvua about what
happened. ופליגא דרבי חייא בר יוסף. u-pliga d'Rabbi Chiyya bar Yosef. And
that argues on
רבי חייא בר יוסף. Rabbi Chiyya bar Yosef. דאמר רבי חייא בר
יוסף עירוב פרשיות כתיב כאן. d'amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Yosef eiruv parshiyos
ksiv kan. The whole, it's just separate פרשיות parshiyos that have been
conflated together here and it's two separate things going on and you
can't read them together. There's מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzas, which is in
a case about a loan, and there the type of a שבועה
shvua you take is if you say yes, I borrowed 50, but
no, you never gave me the other 50. It doesn't have to
be 50-50, it could be 20-80 or 80-20. Okay, so the כי
הוא זה ki hu zeh is a פרשה parsha about a loan.
And then you have the case about a פיקדון pikadon
where this oath Michael is taking is about what happened to the
פיקדון pikadon and it doesn't require anything else. Okay, so it's two
separate things are going on here. וכי כתיב כי הוא זה אמלוה
הוא
דכתיב.
v'chi ksiv ki hu zeh amilva
hu d'ksiv. So when there's an idea of admitting 50 and denying
50 or whatever, מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzas, that's by a loan. When
we're dealing with a פיקדון pikadon and Michael says some accident happened
or it was נגנב, nignav, in that case he takes the שבועה
shvua even if that's the only thing that's being said. All right,
I'll tell you what the big תוספות Tosfos talks about in a
minute, let's just read this גמרא. Gemara. ומאי שנא מלוה? u-mai shna
milva? Now why by מלוה milva do you need a מודה במקצת
modeh b'miktzas and you don't need a מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzas by
פיקדון? pikadon? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says now I want us
first, okay, so let's read through, there's two cases of a פיקדון,
pikadon, one... Say Michael, where's the where's the iPod I gave you
to watch? So he could say oh, terrible thing, it was נגנב.
nignav. That's one case, that's a classic שבועת שומרים. shvuas shomrim. He
admits that he was a שומר shomer and he challenges what happened
and the question is what happened to it, okay? The other question
is, Michael, what happened to that iPhone I gave you to watch?
And Michael says, "What iPhone?" Okay? And basically denies it. Okay, now
that case is much more similar to a מלוה milveh case. He's
denying that I ever gave it to him, okay? And there actually
part of what this big תוספות Tosfos discusses is that if Michael
says "What iPhone?" can I think make him take a שבועה? shvuah?
Okay, so רש"י Rashi says yes. If Michael says what hundred dollars,
what loan, he can't unless he admits to half. You need מודה
במקצת. modeh b'miktzat. But if he says "What iPhone? What I wasn't
שומר shomer anything," I can make him take a שבועה shvuah which
is a little crazy cause that means I could go around and
say to every one of you where's the iPhone I gave you,
where's the iPhone, and right and you're all saying you're lying and
I can make all of you take a שבועה. shvuah. Right now
maybe I might have to prove you know I so so it's
so like anyway but that's what רש"י Rashi says by a פקדון
pikadon you can take you don't need מודה במקצת. modeh b'miktzat. Only
by a מלוה. milveh. Okay, so this is only by מלוה. milveh.
תוספות Tosfos says, I'm not going to get into a couple other
but I'm going to tell you the one that makes the most
sense. He says no, no, no. We have to distinguish two cases
of a פקדון. pikadon. When I say "Where's that iPhone I gave
you?" and he says "What iPhone?" okay, that's just like a מלוה.
milveh. That's a question of fundamentally did I give him the object
or not? So in that case if he's he wouldn't take a
שבועה. shvuah. The only time he would take a שבועה shvuah is
if I would say "Where are those two iPhones I gave you?"
and he says "You only gave me one." So that's just like
a מלוה. milveh. That's a case of a פקדון pikadon which is
like a מלוה milveh which is I say I gave you something
and he denies it. So if he denies it completely, he doesn't
take the שבועה. shvuah. If he admits to part and denies part,
he takes the שבועה. shvuah. The case of a פקדון pikadon that
doesn't need מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzat is when he says "Yes, I
was watching your iPhone but it got stolen." And that by the
way makes a lot of sense why he would take a שבועה
shvuah and you'd have to swear. Why? Because you're admitting that you
had it and you're admitting you have an obligation, okay? So does
everybody get it? Right, there's the second case is a classic שומר
shomer case. The other one is transposed to a מלוה milveh case
which is a hundred yeah but I want to leave it at
that anyway. Which is I gave you a hundred and you and
you admit fifty, that's a מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzat, okay, in that
case you swear. And when it's a hundred and you admit to
zero, you don't swear, right? And there's the case of a פקדון.
pikadon. So if it was basically I say two objects I gave
you and you admit to one, you swear. And I say there
was you know two objects and you admit to zero, you don't
swear, okay, because that's exactly like it. If however I say I
gave you
an
object and you
say
נגנב, nignav,
okay, so
in that case oh that's similar to this, you're not admitting to
anything. I say נגנב, nignav, because it's נגנב nignav you have no
liability but you're admitting that you actually had the object and were
a שומר shomer on the object. Okay so this is the case
that you swear even though you're not a מודה. modeh. Was that
רש"י Rashi and תוספות? Tosfos? Yeah, רש"י Rashi would say you would
not swear here. תוספות Tosfos said I mean right the מחלוקת machlokes
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos is this case, okay? רש"י Rashi says
that by a פקדון pikadon you never swear if now I got
lost where I am. רש"י Rashi says by a פקדון, pikadon, excuse
me, you always swear even if you deny ever having had the
פקדון. pikadon. Alright, but תוספות Tosfos says no, so by a פקדון
pikadon when you're questioned about whether you had it or not, that's
just like a מלוה milveh and you're only going to swear if
you concede something. Right, if you deny ever having received it, תוספות
Tosfos says you're not going to swear, it's just like a מלוה.
milveh.
So where as רש"י Rashi says you would.
Right, רש"י Rashi would say you would. So for רש"י Rashi you
always swear by a פקדון. pikadon. Right, רש"י Rashi any claim about
a פקדון pikadon you would swear, whereas תוספות Tosfos makes a lot
more sense. If there's a total denial then it's just like a
מלוה. milveh. Only when either there's a concession that you gave one
and a denial of the other or where there is a concession
that you were watching it and the question is what happened to
it, that's when that's where it's going to be different. Okay, so
that makes a lot of sense. So let's anyway read the גמרא
Gemara now. Okay, וכי כתיב כי הוא זה אמלוה הוא דכתיב. U'chi
kesiv ki hu zeh amilvei hu dechtiv. ומהי שנא מלוה? U'mai shena
milveh? Now
why is מלוה milveh something that you need to be a מודה
במקצת? modeh b'miktzat? כדרבה, K'dirabba, דאמר רבה, De'amar Rabba, מפני מה אמרה
תורה, Mipnei mah amrah Torah, מודה במקצת ישבע. modeh b'miktzat yishava.
You know you swear when you concede half, because basically it's also
asking like why are you פטור patur when you say when you
deny the whole thing and you're חייב chayav when you concede half?
Like logically it's almost like a מיגו, migo, right? I could have
denied the whole thing and I'm admitting half, you should you should
trust me on this.
What's the difference of a מיגו? migo?
Well it's not. One way of understanding this question is exactly why
don't you have a מיגו, migo, you could have denied the whole
thing. I had this case once in traffic court, of course unfortunately
the judge did not go to a ישיבה. yeshiva. Anyway like somebody
it's the whole story, but anyway some cop gave me two tickets,
one for talking on my cell phone and one for like entering
into the intersection when there was a pedestrian on the street. And
the second one was like totally bogus, he just was angry at
me or whatever. So anyway I came to challenge it in the
court and I said so the judge says how do you plead?
So I said well, guilty on the cell phone not guilty on
the entering into the intersection and the judge I figured like A,
I really was guilty and B, I figured like I'd get more
credibility, you know, by conceding that. But the judge thought I was
totally nuts and he had never heard of anybody pleading guilty to
any part of a complaint. Like what are you doing? Nobody ever
pleads guilty. Anyway the end of the story was what that the—was
that the cop lost the paperwork so I got off on both
of them. So then after—so then after the cop couldn't produce the
paperwork the judge turned back to me and said "Based on what
you just heard would you care to change your plea?"
So then yeah I think I'll plead not guilty to both. Anyway.
What?
I know. I know. Most of the
time
they won't even show up. I know. Anyway. Okay. So the point
though being that that's the question here, right? So why does מודה
במקצת modeh bemiktzat pay? מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzat should be more believed.
Would you?
So yes. If you say—in my mind it's just this whole בבא
מציעא Bava Metzia like way of thinking, right? It's the whole בבא
מציעא סוגיא. Bava Metzia sugya. Like in the middle. It's a whole
different thing.
Right, well a lot of that has been said about this
פרק.
perek. Okay, we think כזה kehzeh means alone. Is it elsewhere כזה?
kehzeh? No, because it doesn't make any sense here. I mean it's
just complete סברא. sevara. כזה, Kehzeh, the idea that you need to
be a מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzat doesn't make any sense if it's
a question about what happened to the object. You were שומר, shomer,
I'm challenging you what happened, you need to make a שבועה, shevuah,
why do we need this whole structure of a מודה במקצת? modeh
bemiktzat? Take that structure out that's a separate basis. You're asking why
someone would think you need a מודה? modeh? I don't know. I
don't know, because that's the way it's written. I don't know. Okay,
אדרבה ואדרבה. aderaba ve-aderaba. ממאן אמרת דמודה במקצת טעון ישבע? Miman amart
de-modeh bemiktzat taun yishava? Why, when you concede half you pay, why
shouldn't you essentially have like a מיגו? migo? Why
do you make a שבועה shevuah more when you concede than when
you deny the whole thing? Because חזקה אין אדם מעיז פניו בפני
בעל חובו. Chazakah ein adam meiz panav bifnei baal chovo. Now here's
why. You can't say, "Oh, I could have just as easily denied
the whole thing."
This guy, if he lent you the money, you wouldn't have had
the חוצפה chutzpah to deny it completely. והאי בכולי בעי דנכפריה, ve-hai
be-chulei bei de-nikfreih, you really would have liked to have denied the
whole thing, you know, because you don't want to get out of
paying, but you weren't prepared to. You weren't able to because of
your basic, you know, humanity, your conscience. דהאי דלא כפר, de-hai de-lo
kafar, but the reason that was holding you back was משום דאין
אדם מעיז פניו, mishum de-ein adam meiz panav, because you couldn't be
so brazen. Okay, so you could say, "Oh, I could have just
as easily claimed that believe me." No, you weren't—there was something that
was making it hard for you to do that even if you
would have wanted to. ובכולי בעי דלודי ליה, u-ve-chulei bei de-lodei leih,
and now that your sort of your good angels are taking over,
so some part you're not always—so you really don't want to sort
of, you know, be so brazen, there's a part of you that
really does want to admit to the whole thing. Now, the reason
that we're also saying that a part of you wants to admit
is that if you really were a רשע rasha and wanted to
steal the money, then making you make a שבועה shevuah wouldn't do
any good. Like this is in general the question that the גמרא
בבבא מציעא Gemara be-Bava Metzia has. How does a שבועה shevuah do
any good? If I'm prepared to steal the money, why is a
שבועה shevuah going to make me admit? Okay, and part of the
answer could be sort of like the whole גניבה להדיא gneiva lehadya
discussion before, people are more prepared to transgress, you know, בין אדם
לחברו bein adam le-chavero things than בין אדם למקום. bein adam la-Makom.
You more sooner be a גנב ganav or גזלן gazlan than make
a false שבועה, shevuah, so a שבועה shevuah will make you admit.
But the other answer could be you're not really fully being a
גנב ganav or גזלן gazlan here anyway. I'm just buying time, okay?
And I really would never—I'm not such a bad guy, ever really
would not pay you—pay you up. I'm just denying it to buy
time. And the שבועה shevuah is forcing me to—to, you know, stay—to
come forth right now. So therefore, part of me wants to completely
deny, but I'm not able to do that. And therefore, part of
me wants to really even admit to it.
Why just because but I'm—right, this is במלווה.
be-milveh. Right, this is מלווה.
milveh. ובכולי בעי דלודי ליה. u-ve-chulei bei de-lodei leih. והאי דכפר ליה
במקצת, ve-hai de-kafar leih be-miktzat, so then why am I denying? סבר
אם מודינא ליה בכולי, savar im modina leih be-chulei, because as soon
as I admit that I owe you the money, תבע לי בכולי,
tava li be-chulei, he's going to make me pay the money,
and אשתמיט לי מיניה השתא, ishtamit li mineih hashta, and I don't
have the money on me, so let me at least buy, you
know, buy a little time now. אדהוו לי זוזי ופרענא, ad de-havu
li zuzei u-farana, the 50 now and I'll find the money and
then I'll say "Oh yeah I do remember I did actually borrow
the other 50," you know, but it'll buy me some time. And
therefore, that's why a person can rationalize and would be willing to
admit half and not say "I could have just as easily denied
it," and why even though he's admitting half, the שבועה shevuah will
do some good because he's still a good guy. רמי רחמנא שבועה
עילויה, remi rachmana shevuah ileiveih, and therefore the Torah imposed a שבועה
shevuah on him כי היכי דלודי ליה ki heichi de-lodei leih in
order to make him admit. And that's why מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzat
makes a שבועה shevuah and a כופר הכל kofer hakol does not
make a שבועה. shevuah. כי היכי דלודי ליה בכוליה. ki heichi de-lodei
leih be-chuleih. Now the גמרא Gemara concludes, ובגבי מלווה הוא דאיכא למימר
הכי. u-ve-gabei milveh hu de-ika lemeimar hachi. This we can say by
a מלווה, milveh, that the being in this middle state like is
a more, you know, makes more sense to make a שבועה shevuah
than total denial.
אבל גבי בפיקדון aval gabei be-fikadon מיז ומיז meiz u-meiz be made.
Now the question is why will he be made? What does that
mean? So you could read this: he'll be made because רש"י Rashi
says you did a kind, you did a kindness when I borrowed
money from you, I owe you. When you give me an object
to watch, in a sense, you owe me. So maybe I'm willing
to be כופר הכל kofer hakol and deny it. That's according to
רש"י Rashi who says that if I say to Michael, if Michael
says to me, Dov, where's the iPhone? I say, What iPhone? I
have to take a שבועה shvuah because if I could be a
כופר הכל kofer hakol and I'm not, I have to pay to
be a כופר הכל. kofer hakol. But according to תוספות's Tosafot approach,
no, no, no. If I basically took something from you and we've
got that life, you know, for me to deny to your face
something you know is true, it doesn't matter whether you did a
kindness or not a kindness. I wouldn't do it by a מלווה,
milveh, I wouldn't do it by a פקדון. pikadon. So even by
a פקדון, pikadon, if I say, What iPhone? I don't have to
take a שבועה, shvuah, only if I concede. Because if I were
to say You're totally lying, but we assume I wouldn't normally do
that, if you, I wouldn't lie to your face about that if
I said that like you never gave me anything. It's just like
it. But when I say it got stolen, you don't know I'm
lying. So therefore by a פקדון, pikadon, you make a שבועה, shvuah,
you don't make, so I like תוספות's Tosafot explanation again, and also
by the way all together, and another גמרא Gemara support it, that
whether a מלווה milveh or a פקדון, pikadon, if you deny fundamentally
that you got it, then you're כופר הכל, kofer hakol, you don't
take a שבועה. shvuah. If you concede you got something, then you're
מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzat, you do. But by a פקדון pikadon when
there's a question what happened, where you concede that you have an
obligation to watch, and where the other guy doesn't know whether you're
lying or not, in that case you take a שבועה shvuah even
without any מודה במקצת. modeh b'miktzat. So even though I say I
don't owe you anything because the iPhone got stolen, so then, but
because you don't know if I'm lying and because I'm conceding that
I was watching it, I take a שבועה shvuah without a מודה
במקצת. modeh b'miktzat. Do you have a question, Chava?
I have two questions. One, and I might be missing this completely,
but if we say he can't, you can't make him give a
שבועה shvuah if he denies everything, he could still take him to
court? You could say that instead of taking him to court.
Well, taking him to court, but good luck.
I mean, yeah, well, good luck.
Right. Okay. And then the other thing was, didn't we say that
there was at least in some cases some time in between where
he made him take a שבועה shvuah and where he was going
to give him back the thing, right? Because something happened on the
way to him giving it back in a couple of cases before,
no?
Like ההיא דחייבוהו לשלומי לא? hahi d'hayvuhu l'shalumi lo? That's after the
judgment has been passed.
Oh, that's after the judgment. Oh, right.
Okay. Okay, so, alright, well so much for catching up. תני רמי
בר חמא, Tani Rami Bar Chama, ארבעה שומרים צריכין כפירה במקצת והודאה
במקצת. arba shomrim tzrichin kfirah b'miktzat v'hoda'ah b'miktzat. Okay, so now it's
sort of following up on the first claim that you need the
מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzat structure, okay, he's saying the same thing, not
like we just said. He says to make a שבועת השומרים, shvuat
hashomrim, whatever type of a שומר shomer you are, whether you say
נגנב nignav or נאנס ne'enas or whatever, שבורה ומתה ונשבה, shevurah u-metah
v'nishba, I say whatever happened to my object, he says oh, such
a terrible thing happened whatever, I can't make you take a שבועה.
shvuah. I have to take you on your word unless there's a
whole מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzat framing the whole case, okay? Like I
gave you three cows, one you admit, one you deny, and one
you say something happened to it. Okay, ואלו הן, v'eilu hein, שומר
חנם והשואל נושא שכר והשוכר. shomer chinam v'hashoel nosei sachar v'hasocher. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava,
so let's just read through, this is obviously going like the first
opinion, it said you need the מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzat structure, and
let's just see the פסוקים. pesukim. מאי טעמא דרמי בר חמא, Mai
ta'ama d'Rami Bar Chama, what's the reasoning? שומר חנם בהדיא כתיב ביה:
shomer chinam b'hedya ketiv bei: כי הוא זה, ki hu zeh, like
we said at the original statement. שומר שכר shomer sachar יליף yalif
נתינה נתינה netinah netinah משומר חנם, mi-shomer chinam, because it says כי
יתן איש אל רעהו כסף או כלים ki yitein ish el re'ehu
kesef o keilim and it says כי יתן איש אל רעהו שור
חמור שה לשמר. ki yitein ish el re'ehu shor chamor seh li-shmor.
One is by שומר חנם, shomer chinam, one is by שומר שכר.
shomer sachar. They both say כי יתן, ki yitein, so we link
them.
שואל, shoel, וכי ישאל, v'chi yishal, after one of the cases of
שמירה shmirah it says and if somebody borrows, so that's a linking,
ו מוסיף על ענין ראשון. vav mosif al inyan rishon. So the
same way by the שומרים shomrim you needed a, you needed a
מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzat structure, here too you need a מודה במקצת
modeh b'miktzat structure. שוכר, socher, how about a person who rents? אי
למאן דאמר I lemant d'amar כשומר שכר, k'shomer sachar, if you say
his liability is equal to that as a paid watcher, היינו שומר
שכר, haynu shomer sachar, so we already know for הלכה halacha a
paid watcher. אי למאן דאמר I lemant d'amar כשומר חנם, k'shomer chinam,
if his liability is that of a, of somebody who watches it
for free, היינו שומר חנם. haynu shomer chinam. Okay, so I guess
we will end here, unfortunately still not fully caught up, but at
least that ends this discussion of to make a שבועת השומרים, shvuat
hashomrim, you also need the structure of a מודה במקצת. modeh b'miktzat.
Very, very strange that you would, but that's where the פסוקים pesukim
are.
כי הוא זה. ki hu zeh. כי הוא זה, ki hu zeh,
yeah, oh שומר חנם shomer chinam is the original
place, yeah.